Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna,
Arya Nagarjuna, and
this is the tenth class.
We're going to talk about
BCINGS PA DANG THAR PA BRTAG PA
Say BCINGS PA [students repeat], DANG
THAR PA, BRTAG PA.
What's BRTAG PA?
[students responding indistinctly]
In Sanskrit.
PARĪKṢĀ (PARIKSHA).
Okay, an investigation
of BCINGS PA and THAR PA.
BCINGS PA means bondage, like
being chained up in the jail,
and THAR PA means freedom.
Now we're going to talk
about the emptiness of
being chained into sansara
and the emptiness of getting
free from those chains.
And let's go to the first verse,
which is really only half a verse,
and it starts with GAL TE.
The guy, you know, Nagarjuna
is asking the other guy,
"Who goes around in sansara?"
Who goes around the circle of sansara?
Who is it that circles
around in sansara, right?
And it's an interesting question.
And by the way, if you don't understand
who it is that circles around in sansara,
that causes you to circle
around in sansara [laughs].
So it's kind of a good question.
All right, so ,GAL TE
'DU BYED 'KHOR ZHE NA,
,DE DAG RTAG NA MI 'KHOR TE,
So GAL TE means, all right,
Nagarjuna's talking to the other guy,
"So who is it that wanders
around in sansara?"
And the other guy says 'DU BYED
which is a confusing answer
because 'DU BYED means factors.
And in fact, it's, for example,
the name for the second
link in the Wheel of Life,
which is fresh karma,
and it has nothing to do with that here.
Here it means PHUNG PO.
The body and mind.
Yeah, I like to call it
body and mind nowadays
because it's just easier.
It's exactly what we call body and mind.
So if you say the thing that
circles around in sansara
is the body mind complex, the
body and the mind together,
'KHOR ZHE NA
if that's what circles around in sansara,
are you thinking of body and mind
as something unchanging or changing?
When you answer me, when I ask you
who is it that travels through sansara,
who is it that goes from birth to birth,
and you say it's body and mind,
it's Michael's body and mind,
and then I say, "Well is
that an unchanging thing
or is that a changing thing?"
And Nagarjuna typically
covers either answer.
So the other guy says it's unchanging.
It's an unchanging thing.
Oh! DE DAG RTAG NA MI 'KHOR TE
If the body and mind of
Michael are unchanging,
and by the way, it shades
into permanent, right?
The way that some people
mistranslate the word.
It shades into permanent.
If it's Michael's permanent body and mind
that keep traveling around sansara,
RTAG NA MI 'KHOR
then it cannot circle.
- Why?
- Because it's RTAG PA,
because it's unchanging.
When you circle, you change.
By circling you change.
Circling means you change.
You can't travel somewhere
else if you don't change.
At least you have to change
where you put your bottom.
Something's going to
change if you're traveling.
So therefore, it cannot be Michael,
unchanging Michael's body and mind,
which goes from birth to birth.
Then the other guy's
going to come back with,
"Okay, I change my story.
It's the body and mind which is changing."
And there's the next verse, yay.
And by the way, the
second half of the verse
gets split again.
So first part of the
second half of the verse is
,MI RTAG NA YANG 'KHOR MI 'GYUR,
,MI RTAG NA YANG 'KHOR MI 'GYUR
If you say Michael's body
and mind are changing,
then they can't circle
around sansara either.
- Why?
- Because they blink out of
existence every millisecond.
Okay? They last:
@SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS ...
Definition of impermanent, changing.
SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS
Say SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS
[students repeat]
@SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS
@
It could be a good song,
@SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS...
It means that thing which
comes into existence
and goes out of existence
SKAD CIG -- instant by instant,
SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS
So how could that have
a sustained circling
if it's going out of
existence every millisecond?
How can something which
goes out of existence
every millisecond go in a circle?
It's not possible.
- Why?
- Because each millisecond
of Michael's body and mind
is separated from the millisecond
just before that, right?
And we're already
talking, we spent so long
talking about SAṂSARGA (SANSARGA),
Christina, SANSARGA.
- [Christina] Flowing together.
Yeah, so if Geshe-la's mind body is
ta da, ta da, ta da
then there's a separation
between each instant,
and then there's no reason why this one
should go to that one
because they never touch.
So this one could change
to Tim's body and mind,
you know, why not?
Because those are not connected either.
So if Michael's body
and mind go like this,
then why can't Michael's
body and mind go like this
and become Tim the next instant? Why?
There's no reason why it shouldn't be Tim
because Tim's also
disconnected from Geshe-la.
If Geshe-la's disconnected from Geshe-la,
and Geshe-la can go moment
to moment like that,
then Geshe-la's body and mind
can become Tim's body and mind,
and I can go over there
and join Tim's sansara.
Right, got it?
If they're separated, anything can happen
and it can't be connected.
It cannot be a flow.
- Why?
- Because that would be unchanging,
and then you don't have
different lifetimes.
It's just, you're stuck in
the same moment all the time,
like gopher's day, what's it called?
- [Woman] Groundhog Day.
- Groundhog Day, right. [laughs]
All right, next verse.
Where is that?
Oh, we are supposed to
have a picture, right?
Let's do the circle, or the second,
I see it's the second clock.
And Choney Lama says, look,
if Geshe-la's body and mind
only lasts for one millisecond,
how could it have time to go in a circle?
There's no circle if
there's only a single point.
You can't draw a circle with single point,
with one single point.
All right, next verse.
,SEMS CAN LA YANG RIM 'DI MTSUNGS,
SEMS CAN means a living being.
You can say sentient being,
I don't like the word
because it's not English.
We don't say that in English.
How's your sentient being mother?
So anyway, it's just a living being.
SEMS CAN LA YANG, RIM
means what? Like Lam Rim.
Steps, okay.
And in Nagarjuna, RIM
has a special meaning,
and it means the steps to
an argument I just gave you.
You know, those steps to
the last argument is called,
in Nagarjuna, is called RIM.
When you see RIM in Nagarjuna,
think: steps to my last argument.
So what's it mean here?
If you say the person, if
you say what travels around
the circle, the Wheel of Life,
is not Geshe-la's body and mind,
but it's rather Geshe-la,
then RIM MTSUNGS, same argument.
Go back to the same
argument. Which is what?
What's the first question Nagarjuna asked?
Now, don't forget, we
finished body and mind,
now the guy says, "Okay, okay,
body and mind cannot circle.
So Geshe-la circles, it's Geshe-la."
Okay, so let's do the same arguments.
We asked him two questions.
If you say it's Geshe-la that's
circling around in sansara,
are you talking about a
Geshe-la who is unchanging?
He starts with unchanging,
I don't know why.
- Are you talking about a
Geshe-la who is unchanging?
- Oh yeah, yeah, it's Geshe-la unchanging.
- Then how can he go in a circle,
because he's in the
same point all the time
because he's the same guy.
He doesn't become an animal
or a deva or hell being,
he's just always Geshe-la.
So he can't, he can't change.
So what's his second RIM PA?
Or are you saying Geshe-la is
changing?
In which case he is random
moments of Geshe-la.
And then in that case,
which we already proved
with our touching arguments,
contact arguments, then
there's no necessary connection
between Geshe-la moment one
and Geshe-la moment two.
Geshe-la moment one could
become Tim moment two.
And then who's circling?
Therefore, nobody's in sansara.
Nobody's traveling
around the Wheel of Life.
- Why?
- It's not Geshe-la's body and mind,
and it's not Geshe-la. - Why?
- Because it's not
Geshe-la's body and mind
which is changing or unchanging,
and it's not Geshe-la who's
changing or unchanging.
There's nothing else.
Nobody's circling in sansara.
All right, we got a picture.
By the way, Choney Lama
likes to go to the idea of...
He says, "Don't forget
when we say Geshe-la,
as opposed to Geshe-la's body and mind,
we're kind of talking about a soul.
Is there some mega Geshe-la
who continues from birth to birth.
He wouldn't look like Geshe-la.
It's independent of body and mind.
There's some inner soul
or essence of Geshe-la
which takes different
bodies and minds, right?
Which throws, who dumps
the old body and mind
and takes a new body and mind.
So there's some kind of Geshe-la
independent of Geshe-la's body and mind.
There's a third part to
Geshe-la which is, you know,
"super inner Geshe-la",
and then the inner Geshe-la
takes bodies and minds,
and keeps going like that.
That's what the second argument's about.
[students speaking indistinctly]
We're going to get there.
In fact, that's the whole chapter.
Don't cheat, all right, here we go.
That's the whole chapter actually.
Good question.
All right, here we go.
Next verse.
,GAL TE GANG ZAG 'KHOR ZHE NA,
,PHUNG PO SKYE MCHED KHAMS RNAMS LA,
,DE NI RNAM PA LNGAS BTZAL NA,
,MED NA GANG ZHIG 'KHOR BAR 'GYUR,
This part has two verses.
Here's the first verse.
GAL TE GANG ZAG 'KHOR ZHE NA
Then the guy's insistent.
No, it's Geshe-la.
The GANG ZAG, the PURUṢA (PURUSHA).
It's Geshe-la that goes from life to life.
He dumps bodies and minds and
he takes new bodies and minds.
It's like some guy in high
school with his girlfriends
or some lady in high
school with her boyfriends.
He dumps one body and mind
and then he takes another one,
then he takes another one.
But he continues through
high school, right?
Okay, so the guy says
no, no, it is Geshe-la
who goes from lifetime to lifetime.
Then let's examine Geshe-la's relationship
with his body and mind.
Let's examine Geshe-la's, if
it's Geshe-la who keeps going
and getting rid of this body and mind
and picking up a new body and mind,
well then what's the relationship
between Geshe-la and the body and mind?
Because there are some relationships
he cannot have with the body and mind
and still switch bodies and minds.
If Geshe-la is the body and mind,
then he can't dump the body and mind
and go to the next birth
because he would be gone.
If he is his body and
mind, and he gives up
a body and mind to take
on the next body and mind,
then Geshe-la cannot be the body and mind.
He's got to be some super
guy who takes bodies
and takes minds, right?
So what's the relationship?
Nagarjuna says, "Okay, okay".
Geshe-la keeps going, right?
- Yeah.
- Geshe-la takes bodies and minds?
- Right.
- So Geshe-la cannot be
his body and mind, right?
- Why?
- Because he dumps them and
then he goes somewhere else.
If he was his body and mind and
he dumped his body and mind,
he'd be gone.
Got it?
There's no Geshe-la who
takes a body and mind
because he is his body and mind.
We better look at the relationship
between Geshe-la and his body and mind.
And then he says RNAM PA LNGAS BCOL
all the texts say RNAM PA LNGAS BCOL
which is total misspelling.
By the way, I got to fix it.
So Tim, if you can imagine the letter
CA - ཅ, first column,
with a naro is CO - ཅོ, right?
But if you draw the
naro with only one horn.
By the way, naro means horns.
So then what's it become?
A CA with a little flag on the side,
becomes TZA - ཙ, yeah, okay.
All the texts say BCOL - བཅོལ,
and they're all wrong, it's a BTZAL- བཙལ.
Okay, so that's the first problem.
You can spend two days looking up
BCOLs in dictionaries,
and you won't figure it out.
And all the carvings are wrong.
Which is irritating for somebody.
DE NI RNAM PA LNGAS
BTZAL NA, okay? If you...
BTZAL means like PHYAG 'TSAL.
What's 'TSAL in PHYAG 'TSAL?
[students responding indistinctly]
But what's it really mean?
To seek a boon from the hand of Lama.
So BTZAL means to seek, to look.
So here it means to look.
RNAM PA LNGA -- five different ways.
There's five different
possible relationships
between Michael and
Michael's body and mind.
Let's look at all five.
If you say it's Michael who
goes from birth to birth
and he picks up new bodies and minds,
then let's look at the
possible relationships
between Michael and his body and mind.
Now Nagarjuna doesn't...
[students responding indistinctly]
tell you what the five are. [laughs]
He never mentions the five.
He never tells you what's the five.
So here's Geshe-la, you
know, late at night,
oh my God, where's the five?
What do you do when you're
Geshe-la and it's late at night
and you have to talk in the morning?
[students responding indistinctly]
You go to Gofer. You go to the database.
And I went to the database
and the first answer I got was Rendawa.
We call Jetsun Rendawa.
Who's Jetsun Rendawa, do you know?
He's a Sakya master who was
the teacher of Tsongkapa.
He's one of the main
teachers of Tsongkapa.
And they started out as
teacher and disciple,
later they teamed up as a teaching team
and they used to teach Vinaya together
and stuff like that.
So, and by the way, Rendawa wrote
an extraordinary commentary
to the Letter to a Friend.
Short, sweet, precise.
So anyway, the first... and
he also wrote a commentary
to Nagarjuna's Wisdom,
which is short and precise,
concise and precise.
So, you know, first I went there,
and I worked on him for a while,
and then I went to Tsongkapa
who wrote a commentary
on Nagarjuna's "Wisdom", called...
- [Woman] Ocean.
- Yeah, the Ocean of Reasoning.
You know, that's the ship that we're in.
We're trying to cross that ocean.
And so altogether I got some good answers.
And that's the beautiful
thing about this text,
everyone has tried to explain it,
and it's hard, it's really hard.
So there's maybe hundreds of
commentaries on this text.
Chandrakirti tried to explain it, right?
So here we go.
So here's the five possible relationships
between Michael and
Michael's body and mind.
Here's the five. And where did I end up?
Oh, to be fair to Nagarjuna,
he already gave us the five
in his text, and we forgot.
He gave it long ago.
He was talking about the relationship
between something and something.
What is it?
Between the fire and the firewood,
and he already covered this point.
That's where, that's
why, he's not being lazy
when he says there's five
possible relationships.
He already covered this point
between the fire and the firewood.
He already covered this point.
So he's probably sitting impatiently
saying, "Don't ask me stupid,
go back to verse #14 in
chapter 10." I went and got it,
and "I discussed it already there.
So don't tell me I didn't
tell you what the five are.
I was hoping you would remember."
So here they are, and you know,
you can go through them quickly
and you say, yeah, yeah,
and then you just don't
think about it anymore.
But let's think about it carefully.
Let's start with Tim. Is
Tim his body and mind?
In this discussion.
Don't forget, the discussion
is in the context of
how does Tim go from birth to birth
in the Wheel of Life.
So this is a pretty easy question.
Is Tim,
Is Tim's body and Tim's mind right now,
is that all there is to Tim?
No, because if it dies, then Tim's gone
and there's no one to go through sansara.
So it can't be that Tim
equals Tim's body and mind
because somebody has to
take the body and mind
and somebody has to
drop the body and mind.
Let's go on to Pachi, number two.
Pachi. Is Pachi completely
separate from his body and mind?
Look, he just fell off his
body and mind [laughs].
No, he has to have some connection, right?
There has to be some connection, right?
Otherwise you would be Tim.
Otherwise Pachi would
be Tim. I mean he'd just
glom on to the nearest
body and mind [laughs].
So there's got to be some Pachi
who's not separate from his body and mind.
There has to be a Pachi who
has some kind of connection
with his body and mind.
You can say there's a separate Pachi
from his body and mind,
but somehow he has to be
intertwined with his body and mind.
Otherwise he'd just get intertwined
with Rebecca's body and mind,
and then you'd have trouble combing
your hair and everything.
And you would have a beard and...
There's all kinds of
philosophical problems. [laughs]
Okay, so Tim is not his body and mind,
but Pachi is not completely
separate from his body and mind.
He's got some connection to it.
Okay, third possibility.
Does Rebecca's body and
mind somehow have Rebecca?
You see, let's switch it this way.
So we're not talking about does
Rebecca have body and mind.
Does the body and mind over there
somehow reach out and hold Rebecca?
That's a weird idea.
That's the third possibility of the five.
Somehow your body and
mind have attracted you,
and your body and mind's
gravity sucked in Rebecca,
and Rebecca's stuck to
Rebecca's body and mind.
That's the third possibility,
which is kind of silly,
but it's not completely silly.
A fourth possibility, Pau ready?
Pau doesn't depend on her body and mind.
You can do anything to her body and mind,
and it doesn't effect Pau.
You can get a virus, you
can get a vaccination,
and Pau doesn't care.
Pau's a different entity
from body and mind.
But Pau doesn't rest on her body and mind.
That's the fourth possibility, right?
We've got four, right?
One, two, three, four.
Okay, Christina, you ready?
Christina's body and mind
don't depend on Christina.
So Christina can go away and
Christina's body and mind
will still be in the chair, typing away.
Okay, all right, that's
the fifth possibility.
And all five possibilities
are kind of on untenable.
They're not, they're kind of impossible.
It doesn't seem possible.
What were you thinking when you thought
you were traveling through sansara?
What were you thinking
was your relationship
to your body and mind?
Could you dump your body and mind
and there's still something
about you that can go on
and take another body and mind?
Can you exist without a body and mind?
Can the body and mind exist without you?
Can it go on without you?
You know, when you think about
going through the Wheel of Life,
traveling through sansara, you
didn't really think it out.
That's what Nagarjuna's saying.
Maybe you have some idea.
I think most of us feel,
at least I grew up in a Christian culture,
Judeo-Christian culture.
I feel like there's some Michael's soul
that takes the body and mind
and holds it for a while
and then they get separated
and the soul goes on
and then the soul has to
find a new body and mind,
or something like that.
And in that case, you could do
things to the body and mind,
you could abuse the body and mind,
and the soul is somehow beyond all that.
Nothing happens to the
soul, something like that.
The Judeo-Christian culture
has an opinion on this question.
And so we have it because
we grew up in this culture.
But if you really examine
it, is it defensible?
Is it make sense?
Are you totally independent
from your body and mind?
Is there a Rebecca which is totally,
is totally unaffected
by the body and mind?
All right, and if you're interested,
go back to verse 14 of chapter 10
where they discuss whether
the wood is the fire,
and that's the same argument.
And that's why Nagarjuna didn't bother.
GAL TE MANG POS BKUR BA ,I'm sorry, no.
We finished that.
All right.
Let's go to...
[student speaking indistinctly]
'DU BYED
We didn't do NYE BAR LEN, verse three?
Oh right, you're right, the second half.
Oh yeah, that's a nasty one.
[laughing]
I don't know why I skipped it.
Let's go back, I know
what you're talking about.
,NYE BAR LEN NAS NYER LEN PAR,
,'KHOR NA SRID PA MED PAR 'GYUR,
,SRID MED NYE BAR LEN MED NA,
,DE GANG CI ZHIG 'KHOR BAR 'GYUR,
This is tricky because NYE BAR LEN PA
is a very difficult word
in Buddhist philosophy
which means to take on closely.
NYE BAR LEN PA
But it means to take on a
new body and mind at rebirth.
So, okay, so even that word suggests what?
[students responding indistinctly]
Yeah, somebody takes it on.
Okay, so the Buddhist, the
ancient Buddhist expression
for rebirth is called
embracing another one.
It's called embracing another one.
So it means another body and mind.
So then Nagarjuna uses
it for the word rebirth.
He uses it for the word rebirth.
He says, "So is it that a rebirth...
What happens from rebirth to rebirth?
Let's look at that, and then we can decide
your relationship. We can
decide the relationship
of your body and mind with you.
Let's look at how you go
from rebirth to rebirth,
and then we can decide
what's the relationship
between Tim and Tim's body and mind.
So he says here NYE BAR
LEN NAS NYER LEN PAR
when you go from one identity
to another, for example,
and then Choney Lama says,
I don't know why he says,
"If you go from a human birth
to a deva", to a deva birth,
to a divine, temporary
suffering being birth,
which kind of assumes that
we are meditating. Okay?
'KHOR NA SRID PA MED PAR 'GYUR,
then there's no SRID PA in 'KHOR BA.
'KHOR BA means sansara,
SRID PA here means, and
again you need Choney Lama.
It doesn't mean SRID PA
which means sansara,
like SRID PA'I 'KHOR LO,
BHAVACAKRA, the Wheel of Life,
it doesn't mean that here.
Here it means BAR SRID.
And since you guys studied Abhidharma
you know what's a BAR
SRID, BAR DO SRID PA.
[students responding indistinctly]
A being in the BAR DO, yeah,
it's called a BAR SRID.
It's called a BAR guy.
[laughs] BAR guy.
It's not that kind of bar guy.
BAR SRID
So KHOR NA SRID PA MED PAR 'GYUR
If you drop, if you drop, how do you say?
if you drop one body and mind
and then take on another body
and mind in the next moment,
then there's no BAR DO.
That's what he's saying.
Nagarjuna's saying, "Look,
what happens when you,
how do you go from one
birth to another birth?"
Oh, and the other guy says,
"Well, you just drop your body and mind
and then you pick up a new
one in the next millisecond."
- Okay, then there's no BAR DO
which is against Buddhist teaching.
There should be a BAR DO.
There should be a... for
most kinds of rebirth.
Then the guy says, no, no, no.
,SRID MED NYE BAR LEN MED NA,
,DE GANG CI ZHIG 'KHOR BAR 'GYUR,
How can you say there's a cycle of rebirth
if there's an interruption
between the rebirth?
How can you say there's a
constant continuation of rebirth
if it's a discontinuation?
If you say no, no, no, there's a BAR DO,
well then there's no connection,
no necessary connection between
dropping this body and
mind, and picking up
your next body and mind,
because there's a gap.
And you can't have a
circle where there're gaps.
That doesn't make a circle.
Circles should be [vocalizing],
They should go like that.
If there is a BAR DO,
then there's no 'KHOR BA.
If you drop your body and mind,
and there's a gap until you
pick up your new body and mind,
then you can't have a cycle.
That's just a bunch of interrupted
vignettes or something.
It's not a cycle.
It doesn't fit the meaning of a cycle.
Cycles should be [vocalizing], same thing
over and over again, like, I don't know,
troubles with the tech
equipment or something.
you know, shit just keeps happening.
Sorry, I'm not saying it did, I'm saying,
by the way I'm very grateful for the tech,
God bless the tech.
So we covered that second verse.
Let's go to the next verse.
Yeah, and it's a very interesting segue.
Sometimes Nagarjuna just
moves on to another topic,
meaning he thinks the case is closed.
We're like... and he's
like, "Come on, you got it,
you guys got it.
Nobody takes on the body and
mind and the body and mind
doesn't have anybody to take it on.
Let's move on."
[students laughing]
Okay, and you're like oh, wait!
So here we go to the next verse.
He's moving to a huge separate topic.
,'DU BYED MYA NGAN 'DA' BAR NI,
,JI LTA BUR YANG MI 'THAD DO,
,SEMS CAN MYA NGAN 'DA' BAR YANG,
,JI LTA BUR YANG 'THAD MI 'GYUR,
Let's stop talking about who it is
that takes on bodies and minds.
Let's start talking about who
it is that reaches nirvana.
Who breaks out of this cycle?
What's happening then?
What's happening when you
break out of the cycle?
We discussed the cycle,
it doesn't make sense.
You cannot take on a body and mind
and you cannot not take
on a body and mind.
Something's fishy.
Enough, let's go on to,
well who gets enlightened,
who gets to nirvana?
'DU BYED MYA NGAN 'DA' BAR NI
What's 'DU BYED mean this chapter?
For $100.
Factor.
But what's it mean in this chapter?
Cancel the bet.
PHUNG PO -- the body and mind.
So the word factors in this chapter
refers to your body and mind.
It just means changing stuff,
the changing part of Rebecca.
Rebecca as a soul is this stainless steel,
unchanging egg shape, and
then Rebecca's body and mind,
and he calls it changing
stuff about Rebecca,
which is the stuff you
take on and you drop
from life to life.
So he says, look, does the,
is it Rebecca's body and
mind that goes to nirvana?
What part of Rebecca goes to nirvana?
Is it Rebecca's body and mind?
JI LTA BUR YANG MI 'THAD DO
Now, now it's this kind
of frustrating thing
with Nagarjuna.
He says no, it's not Becky's body and mind
that goes to nirvana.
- Why?
- Because it's self-existent, please.
It's not her body and mind
which blinks out or something.
- Why?
- Because it's self-existent,
it doesn't depend on anything else.
It doesn't depend on mental seeds.
It's coming from its own side.
It doesn't ever blink out.
It's coming illogically from its own side,
and it's going to stay
illogical from its own side.
And nothing illogical's
going to make it disappear.
It's an illogical, metal,
unchangeable egg shape
called Rebecca.
So forget it.
And Nagarjuna's kind of
frustrating that way.
This book is kind of frustrating that way.
Whenever he gets in a corner, he says,
"Well, anyway it can't happen."
And you say, Why?
And he says because you
think it's coming...
because you think the
husband in the kitchen
comes from his side. "na, na, na, na, na."
[students laughing]
Then you're like oh man, come on.
If the husband in the kitchen
is upset because he had traffic at work,
then your...
then your body and mind
cannot go to nirvana.
That's his argument.
If your husband is coming from his side,
then your body and mind cannot
be what goes to nirvana.
- Why?
- Because it also exists
from it's own side,
and it couldn't change.
It couldn't reach some
elevated place called nirvana
because it couldn't change,
because it's coming from its own side.
The only way anything can
change in the universe
is if your mental seeds change. Got it?
All right, then the guy changes the story.
Oh, it's not Rebecca's body
and mind that goes to nirvana,
it's... what's the other choice?
It's not Rebecca's body and mind-
- [Students] Rebecca.
- It's Rebecca, which he
calls GANG ZAG, PARUSHA.
- Oh no, no, no, I change, I change,
it's not Rebecca's body and
mind that goes to nirvana,
it's "Rebecca".
MYA NGAN 'DA' YANG
JI LTA BUR YANG 'THAD MI 'GYUR
Same problem, please.
Rebecca comes from her own side.
She can't change. She can't go to nirvana.
It's kind of using the
thing he's trying to prove
in the argument, to prove
what he's trying to prove.
It seems a little fishy,
but if it's fishy,
he's proving what he said.
[students responding indistinctly]
Everything's fishy, okay.
Yeah, and the picture is
just kind of artificial here,
but it's to help you remember.
Here's [laughs], here's
Rebecca's body and mind.
It's supposed to be the mind and the body.
And which one gets to nirvana?
I don't know.
All right.
Choney Lama has a particularly
compelling, excuse me,
has a particularly
compelling argument here,
and I would like to read it.
So sometimes it's nice to go
to Choney Lama, let him talk.
We've just been letting Nagarjuna talk.
'DIR 'KHOR MKHAN RANG
BZHIN GYIS MED PAR NGES NA
If it is the case that the 'KHOR MKHAN,
MKHAN, MKHAN is the...
MKHAN is the word you add
to a verb to make it a doer,
like a teacher would be a SLOB MKHAN.
MKHAN is E-R in English, teach-er.
You add E-R to teach, it
makes the person who teaches.
In Tibetan you add MKHAN.
So what's 'KHOR MKHAN?
- [Woman] A circler.
- The circler, yeah,
the guy who goes around in sansara. Good.
'KHOR MKHAN RANG BZHIN
GYIS MED PAR NGES NA
Choney Lama's like, "Why
are we talking about,
"why are we so obsessed
with this person who,
"why are we obsessed with
figuring out who it is
that goes through sansara?"
Because if you can NGES PA,
if you can ascertain that they are
RANG BZHIN GYIS MED PA
[students responding indistinctly]
Yeah, if you can ascertain that the person
who goes around sansara doesn't
exist from their own side,
well then you can stop
going around sansara!
You got it? It's very beautiful.
I'll say it again.
Choney Lama says, "Hey, you want to guess
why we're obsessing about who it is
that circles around in sansara?
And we're like, "I don't know."
He says, "Because we want to see
that they don't have any
nature on their own."
- Well, why?
- Because then you don't have
to circle around sansara!
It's a very beautiful argument.
Got it?
That's why we're having
this long discussion
about who is it that
circles around sansara.
Because by examining your relationship
to your body and mind, you're
suddenly going to figure out
that you are coming from
yourself, your seeds,
and then you don't have to
circle around sansara. Yay!
Okay.
That's so Choney Lama.
All right, next verse.
Now he wants to talk about the concept of
'CHING BA and GROL BA,
and I'd like to skip
to the Sanskrit lesson
which is the next slide.
Mainly I do this for Christina
because she appreciates it.
So we're going to discuss
'CHING BA and GROL BA.
This chapter is called
Bondage and Liberation.
Shackles and Freedom,
or something like that.
And we've been discussing
who is it that's shackled?
Who is it that's in the handcuffs?
And now let's go look
at the Sanskrit words
that are being used here
because then you can
learn some Sanskrit
so when you become Medicine
Buddha, you can speak in Sanskrit.
So here's the first word: BANDHA, BANDHA.
We have them in yoga, right?
Pau, what's a BANDHA?
[students responding indistinctly]
Yeah, a lock. We call it a lock.
Yeah, similar. GRANTHI is more nasty,
GRANTHI is like a knot in the channels.
But BANDHA is a purposeful,
somewhere down here, I don't
know, it's hard for me to do.
You tighten up your belly,
that's a BANDHA, a lock.
Okay, so BANDHA, technical
spelling is the same,
it doesn't have any, it's
all English sound, BANDHA.
The Tibetan is 'CHING BA.
The way I learned 'CHING BA was
from the Tibetan newspapers,
they kept talking about
@'CHING GROL DMAG MI
People's Liberation Army.
The word in Tibetan for
the Chinese National Army
is @'CHING GROL DMAG MI,
shackle-freeing army.
People's Liberation Army.
So 'CHING means shackle.
Okay, 'CHING BA.
So the root is √BANDH,
and it means to bind.
Hey Jigme, did you ever go
to the bus station in India,
and everyone's on strike
and they're all saying,
"BANDH KARO"
We're on strike, we're on strike.
BANDH means, shackle the buses
so they can't get anywhere.
The Indo-European is
√BHENDH, and it came into
bind, band, and bundle.
Okay, so it's easy to see how BANDHA
means being chained to sansara.
Okay, now what's the opposite?
Next slide is MUKTI or MOKṢA (MOKSHA).
The SHA is a retroflex, right?
You've got to turn your
tongue back, MOKSHA MOKSHA
and the Tibetan is GROL
BA as in SGROL MA -- Tara.
And the root is √muc or
√mokṣ which means to release.
I think it's related
to the Indo-European...
there's a MUC which means to be slimy,
like mucus comes from that.
And I think it means to
slide out of sansara,
but I didn't put that here
because it's a little too much.
[students laughing]
On your [laughs]...
And I think that all of them are related
to the Indo-European
√mittere which means to,
and you find it in Latin, right,
to send a message, missive,
mission, to send somebody out.
It means to liberate somebody, got it?
All right, so let's go
back to the verse now
which is going backwards in the slides.
,SKYE 'JIG CHOS CAN 'DU BYED RNAMS,
,MI 'CHING GROL BAR MI 'GYUR TE,
Don't forget that 'DU BYED here
means body and mind.
Spelled a little differently.
How could you remove shackles
from a SKYE 'JIG?
From a person who was going
in and out of existence.
SKYE 'JIG -- minute by
minute, second by second.
How could you liberate a person?
How could you take chains off of a person
which was either unchanging
or changing millisecond by millisecond?
You know, by the time you get
your hands on the shackles,
they changed into somebody else.
So how can you... Who is there?
What body and mind is
there in a sustained way
to take off their shackles?
Because if they're in a sustained way,
that means they're unchanging,
which is impossible.
You can't take shackles off of a person
who is sustained over time
because they cannot change,
and they cannot go from
shackled to unshackled
because they can't change.
You can't take shackles off
of a person who can't change
because taking off shackles
is to change them, got it?
And if they're changing every millisecond,
by the time you get your
hand on the shackles,
it's somebody else's shackles.
Okay, got it?
,SNGA MA BZHIN DU SEMS CAN YANG,
,MI 'CHING GROL BAR MI 'GYUR RO,
SNGA MA BZHIN means, look,
let's follow the same pattern as before.
Now we established
you can't take chains off
of Pachi's body and mind.
- Why?
- Because if they keep going
for any length of time,
they can't change.
And if they don't keep going
for any length of time,
they're somebody else by the
time you get to the shackles.
And if it applies to Seiji, sorry,
Pachi's body and mind,
it also applies to Pachi.
That's the second half of the verse.
He's doing the same RIM PA, right?
- What's that mean?
- [Woman] Steps.
The same, the same,
there's parallel arguments.
Let's treat Pachi's body and mind,
and then let's treat Pachi.
You cannot take chains off
of Pachi's body and mind
because it has to be either
changing or unchanging,
you can't take chains off
something, either one.
And you can't take chains off of Pachi.
Which is that aluminum Rebecca
who goes from life to life
and drops bodies and minds
and takes new ones in
because same problem.
If he's changing, you don't have time
to take his shackles off,
and if he's unchanging
he can't get unshackled
when he used to be shackled
because then he'd be changing, got it?
It don't make sense to say
you can liberate a person.
It don't make sense. Something's wrong.
That's Nagarjuna's, the whole chapter is
it don't make sense that
Pachi got into sansara,
and it don't make sense that you can
get Pachi out of sansara.
Something's going on.
There's a big problem here.
Why does he go to liberation and shackles?
I guess because we're so invested in it.
We're reading his book because
we want to change our life (laughs).
That's why we're reading
the book in the first place.
All right, here we go.
Whoops, we finished the chapter. Yay!
[students laughing]
So, okay, let's wrap up.
If Pachi's the one moving
from lifetime to lifetime,
then I don't know, he's unchanging because
he's the unchanging Pachi who
picks up new bodies and minds
and drops them, and goes and
picks up a new body and mind.
That would imply that Pachi exists
without his body and mind, which is crazy.
Then if there is no Pachi,
who holds his body and mind,
and if Pachi's just his body and mind,
then who goes to the next life?
If this body and mind
died, then Pachi's gone
because he's just his body and mind.
- No, no, Pachi is the soul
who holds onto his body and mind.
- Well then he doesn't change.
Then he's going to be in sansara forever.
Cannot be liberated.
Some kind of problem with Pachi.
Alright, let's go to
the next chapter, yay!